Throughout your career at the CIA, did
you ever come close to getting
assassinated?
>> Oh, twice.
Close. Close. Uh, the first time was in
um in Athens in 2000. I was I was
stationed in Athens as the
counterterrorism
um center representative
and I was there specifically
to work against a group called
Revolutionary Organization 17 November.
This was a group that was so deadly.
They had murdered 28 people. They had
wounded hundreds.
And not only had they never been caught,
we were never able to identify a single
one of them. They would do these they
would do these assassinations in broad
daylight in front of 2,000 people and
nobody saw a thing because they were so
petrified of being the next victim. So,
as a CIA officer, I drove a fully
armored BMW 540. It was the first 540 in
Greece. As a matter of fact, we we
couldn't even insure it because there
were no other 540s. We had to insure it
through a company in Germany. And and I
was always heavily armed. We all were. I
had a 9mm and a tear away fanny pack on
my waist. I had a 38 snubnse on my
ankle. And then just in case things
really went to [__] I had a buck knife
in my back pocket.
So
every day, and this is what we're all
trained to do, every day you leave your
house at a different time and you take a
different route to work every single day
because as soon as you establish a
pattern, they know where to be standing
to kill you as you go through that
intersection.
So the British embassy in uh oh I guess
it was February or March of 2000 got a
new defense atache Steven Saunders and
Steven moved in next door to me. Our our
backyards abudded
and he was just such a lovely guy. He
was the life of the party. So in early
April of 2000, we're at a dinner party
and I was standing with Steve and with
the French defense attaches and the
American defense attache
and he was making fun of me because I
had just gotten my BMW.
And he said, "You Americans are so
paranoid about security." He goes, "This
is an EU country. It's a NATO country.
what are you so afraid of? And they all
chuckle. And I said, "You Brits live in
a dream world. If you think that because
they have palm trees and pretty beaches
that they're not going to kill you if
they have the chance. If they have the
chance, they're going to kill you." We
all laughed again. Two weeks later, I
did something that I had never done
before. I slept through my alarm and I
woke up and I looked at the clock and I
was like, "Oh my god, I slept in." Which
meant I didn't have time to do this
2-hour surveillance detection route. I
just had to get on the main road, go
straight to the embassy. So, I get in
the car, I get on QVCs, it's a parking
lot. And I I was like, "Great.
Now, what am I going to say when I get
there 2 hours late?" Right? And the
thing with GVCS is it had these concrete
jersey barriers. So once you were on,
you were on.
>> You're not getting back off.
>> Can't get back off.
>> So I'm inching, like literally inching.
So I turn the radio on and the the DJ is
saying, uh, avoid Kicas Boulevard. There
was a criminal incident at Felith. And I
thought, huh, I never heard that before.
I wonder what kind of criminal incident
at 9:00 in the morning would jam up
traffic like this. And still inching
down the mountain, another half hour
passes and the guy says, "Avoid GCS
Boulevard. There was a terrorist attack
at Filoth." Well, I definitely had never
heard that before. And he says it just
as I'm approaching this white rover in
the left lane and the cops are putting
tape around it and I saw the license
plate. Now, Athens was so it well was
back then so dangerous for Americans. We
spent more money on security in Athens
than we did in Beirut. That's how
dangerous it was because of this group.
So, we didn't have diplomatic license
plates. It was too dangerous. It would
it would allow them to more easily
identify us as Americans. But the Greeks
in their infinite wisdom
gave literally everybody in the American
embassy license plates that began with
YHB.
Everybody. It was worse than a
diplomatic plate
>> cuz you knew.
>> Yeah. My mine was YHB1 1442. I still
remember it after 25 years. My wife was
YHB 1367.
So I look at this license plate on this
rover and it's YBH
and four numbers. And I thought, "Oh no,
they killed some poor Greek thinking
that it was one of us." And then I
remember, "No, the British embassy is
YBH
and Steve Saunders drives a white
rover." So I called the station and my
boss says, "Where are you?" I said, "I'm
stuck on F on uh KYCS Boulevard, but I
think Steven Saunders was just
assassinated." He said, "Why? What do
you see?" And I I told him, you know,
it's a white rover. I said, "It's just
soaked. The interior's soaked in blood."
and the driver's side windows shot out
and he said, "Okay, get here as quickly
as you can." So, just as I get past the
car, of course, traffic opens up. I run
into the station. Everybody's waiting
for me. So, I told them what happened.
My boss picks up the phone. He calls the
British embassy and this the British the
MI6 secretary answers and uh and he
says, "We think Steven Saunders was just
assassinated." And it's like she didn't
like it didn't register or or she
misheard. And she says, "I'm sorry.
Steven's not in yet today." And he said,
"No, you're not listening to me. We
think Steven was just assassinated." And
she says, "Oh, oh my god, we'll call you
right back." And then she called us back
20 minutes later and she said he had
just died at the Red Cross hospital,
which ironically is next door to the
British Embassy. So several months
passed. Now what 17 November used to do
is they would drop a manifesto. This was
a this was a an incredibly violent
Marxist Leninist um group. They would
drop a manifesto at the site of the hit
or they would put a manifesto in a
garbage can somewhere in the
neighborhood and then call a leftist
newspaper to tell them where the the
garbage can was that they could go
retrieve it. But they didn't leave a
manifesto with him. They had done that
once or twice before, but it was
unusual.
That was in April. On August 16th,
I go into the office and my boss runs
into my office and he says, "Did you see
the manifesto?" And I said, "There was
no manifesto." He said, "No, they
dropped it today." And I said, "No, I
didn't hear anything about it. I didn't,
you know, run my radio in the car
normally." And he said, "They mentioned
you in the manifesto." I said, "What?
Not possible." I said, 'I am more
careful than anybody in this office with
my security. And he hands me the
manifesto and it says in Greek mealas,
we saw the big spy, but he was in an
armored car and we knew he was armed, so
we elected to carry out the
revolutionary sentence on the war
criminal Saunders. And he says, "You got
to go." I said, "Where?" He says,
"Home." Like now. I said, "I just
dropped my kids off at school. I can't
just go." He said, "We'll get your kids.
We'll get your wife. We'll pack your
house out. You got to go to the airport
now." So, they put me in another armored
car. They took me to the airport. They
picked up my wife, picked up my kids.
They get to the airport and my wife
says, "I want a divorce. I can't do this
anymore."
And that was the last day that we, you
know, lived together as husband and
wife. But they didn't get me.